ACTIVITY 2


1. Explain in your own words the relationship between a deck and a card.

The relationship between a deck and a card is an aggregation because a deck has a card within in it.

2. Consider the deck initialized with the statements below. How many cards does the deck contain?
 String[] ranks = {"jack", "queen", "king"};
 String[] suits = {"blue", "red"};
 int[] pointValues = {11, 12, 13};
 Deck d = new Deck(ranks, suits, pointValues);

6 cards

3. The game of Twenty-One is played with a deck of 52 cards. Ranks run from ace (highest) down to 2
(lowest). Suits are spades, hearts, diamonds, and clubs as in many other games. A face card has point
value 10; an ace has point value 11; point values for 2, …, 10 are 2, …, 10, respectively. Specify the
contents of the ranks, suits, and pointValues arrays so that the statement
 Deck d = new Deck(ranks, suits, pointValues);
initializes a deck for a Twenty-One game.

String[] ranks = {"Two", "Three", "Four", "Five", "Six", "Seven", "Eight", "Nine", "Ten",
"Jack", "Queen", "King", "Ace"};
String[] suits = {"Spades", "Heats", "Diamonds", "Clubs"};
int[] pointvalues = {2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 10, 10, 10, 11};
Deck deck = new Deck(ranks, suits, pointValues);

4. Does the order of elements of the ranks, suits, and pointValues arrays matter?

The order of the suits does not matter although the order of the ranks and pointValues do. The rank and its corresponding pointValue must be in the same
index of the lists they are in.


ACTIVITY 3


1. Write a static method named flip that simulates a flip of a weighted coin by returning either
"heads" or "tails" each time it is called. The coin is twice as likely to turn up heads as tails.
Thus, flip should return "heads" about twice as often as it returns "tails."

public static String flip()
{
	if (Math.random() > .66666666666)
	{
		return "tails";
	}
	else
	{
		return "heads";
	}
}

2. Write a static method named arePermutations that, given two int arrays of the same length
but with no duplicate elements, returns true if one array is a permutation of the other (i.e., the
arrays differ only in how their contents are arranged). Otherwise, it should return false.

public static boolean arePermutations(int[] array1, int[]array2)
{	
	int isMatch;
	for (int i = 0; i< array1.length; i++)
	{
		isMatch=0;
		for (int j =0; j < array2.length; j++)
		{
			if (array1[1] == array2[j])
			{
				isMatch++;
			}
			if (isMatch!=1)
			{
				return false;
			}
		}	
	}
	return true;
}

3. Suppose that the initial contents of the values array in Shuffler.java are {1, 2, 3,
4}. For what sequence of random integers would the efficient selection shuffle change values to
contain {4, 3, 2, 1}?

0,1,0

ACTIVITY 5

Buggy1:
Constructor or Method (write method name): .isEmpty
Describe a Possible Code Error:Wrote return false if size != 0 instead of ==0

Buggy2:
Constructor or Method (write method name):.Size
Describe a Possible Code Error: The code sets size to size - 1 instead of the actual size value

Buggy3:
Constructor or Method (write method name): .Shuffle
Describe a Possible Code Error:The code does not use Math.Random so it just sets eac card in the deck to itself and therefore it is not shuffled

Buggy4:
Constructor or Method (write method name): .Deal
Describe a Possible Code Error:The code may deal the card at index 1 instead of index 0



Buggy5:
Constructor or Method (write method name):
Describe a Possible Code Error:












ACTIVITY 6


I won 1 of 5 games

1. List all possible plays for the board 5♠ 4♥ 2♦ 6♣ A♠ J♥ K♦ 5♣ 2♠

Combinations/plays: 5♠ and 6♣, 5♣ and 6♣

2. If the deck is empty and the board has three cards left, must they be J, Q, and K? Why or why not?

Yes, they must be the J, Q, and K because every card that is not in the deck and not on the board must have found it other match(s),
 so the game would have been lost if already if it wasn't the J, Q, and K.

3. Does the game involve any strategy? That is, when more than one play is possible, does it matter
which one is chosen? Briefly explain your answer.

No there is not strategy to the game Elevevns because the cards that you get from the deck to replace a match are already pre set.
If you had two possible combinations then the order that you do the combinations would not matter because you will still get the same exact 4-6 from the pre set order of the deck. 


ACTIVITY 7


1. What items would be necessary if you were playing a game of Elevens at your desk (not on the
computer)? List the private instance variables needed for the ElevensBoard class.

Board to play on(desk), a deck of cards

Instance variables: Deck, cardsOnBoard(the ones on the board)

2. Write an algorithm that describes the actions necessary to play the Elevens game.

Have a deck of cards and deal them out. Then you have the player combine possible matches(two cards that add to 11 or Jack,queen, and king)
and replace them with cards from the deck after the matches were discarded. You continue this process until there are no more matches or until the game has been won(all matches
have been found and the deck is empty)

3. Now examine the partially implemented ElevensBoard.java file found in the Activity7
Starter Code directory. Does the ElevensBoard class contain all the state and behavior
necessary to play the game?Activity 7 - 22 - Elevens Student Lab Guide

Yes, besides the unimplemented methods


4. ElevensBoard.java contains three helper methods. These helper methods are private
because they are only called from the ElevensBoard class.

a. Where is the dealMyCards method called in ElevensBoard?

In the constructor and the newGame method

b. Which public methods should call the containsPairSum11 and containsJQK
methods?

anotherPlayPossible() and isLegal()

c. It’s important to understand how the cardIndexes method works, and how the list that it
returns is used. Suppose that cards contains the elements shown below. Trace the execution
of the cardIndexes method to determine what list will be returned. Complete the diagram
below by filling in the elements of the returned list, and by showing how those values index
cards. Note that the returned list may have less than 9 elements.
 cards -> 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
	J♥ 6♣ null 2♠ null null A♠ 4♥ null
returned ->
list
		0  1  2  3  4 
		0  1  3  6  7 

Activity 7 - 23 - Elevens Student Lab Guide



d. Complete the following printCards method to print all of the elements of cards that are
indexed by cIndexes.
public static printCards(ElevensBoard board) 
{
 List<Integer> cIndexes = board.cardIndexes();
 /* Your code goes here. */
	for (Integer num: cIndexes)
	{
		int number = (int)(num);
		System.out.println(number);
		
	}
}



e. Which one of the methods that you identified in question 4b above needs to call the
cardIndexes method before calling the containsPairSum11 and containsJQK
methods? Why?

anotherPlayPossible() because it needs to check all of the remaining cards at there specific index and check 
whether it containsPairSum11 or containsJQK.

ACTIVITY 8

1. Discuss the similarities and differences between Elevens, Thirteens, and Tens.

For all three games they could all inherit from one Board class because they are very similar and need to deal cards out from a deck on too the board.
They could not inherit from eachother because each one is unique in the fact that the isLegal method and the anotherPlayIsPossible method
would be different. The ways to make a pair are different for each of them.


2. As discussed previously, all of the instance variables are declared in the Board class. But it is the
ElevensBoard class that “knows” the board size, and the ranks, suits, and point values of the
cards in the deck. How do the Board instance variables get initialized with the ElevensBoard
values? What is the exact mechanism?

By using super you can use the constructor of the Board class to do this


3. Now examine the files Board.java, and ElevensBoard.java, found in the Activity8
Starter Code directory. Identify the abstract methods in Board.java. See how these
methods are implemented in ElevensBoard. Do they cover all the differences between Elevens,
Thirteens, and Tens as discussed in question 1? Why or why not?

isLegal and anotherPlayIsPossible are abstract methods in Board.java. These methods are not yet implemented in Activity 8. But they would cover for
all the differences because they are specifically implemented for the type of board you are working with to overide the abstract method of Board.java
each of these implementations account for the differences.

ACTIVITY 9

1. The size of the board is one of the differences between Elevens and Thirteens. Why is size not an
abstract method?

Although the sizes are different, the method of retrieving the size is the same so therefore there does not need to be a more specific method wrote 
within the subclasses. The Board size method is adaquete

2. Why are there no abstract methods dealing with the selection of the cards to be removed or replaced
in the array cards?

Because the process doing this is similar for all types of Boards so it can just be created as one method in the Board class.

3. Another way to create “IS-A” relationships is by implementing interfaces. Suppose that instead of
creating an abstract Board class, we created the following Board interface, and had
ElevensBoard implement it. Would this new scheme allow the Elevens GUI to call isLegal
and anotherPlayIsPossible polymorphically? Would this alternate design work as well as
the abstract Board class design? Why or why not?
 public interface Board
 {
 boolean isLegal(List<Integer> selectedCards);
 boolean anotherPlayIsPossible();
 }

The new interface scheme would work although the current design would work better because you will not have to reimplement the common methods in every 
subclass of Board when it could just be implemented once in the super class.



















